we said that to implement logs easily we
need Atomic instructions that are going
to both read and write memory there are
three main types of such instructions
the first type is an atomic exchange
instruction something like this the
parameters for this instruction look
like the parameters for a load or a
store but what an exchange does it does
both a load and a store at the same time
so that it swaps the content of R1 with
the contents of the memory location that
IT addresses so a load would read this
and put it in R1 a store would take
what's in R1 and put it here an exchange
swaps the contents of the tool so the
register gets what was in the memory
location and the memory location gets
what was in the register if we have an
atomic exchange what we can do is put
one into R1 and then repeatedly as long
as R1 is equal to one exchange R1 with
our lock variable so this is the idea R1
being one we are exchanging our R1 with
the lock variable we start out with one
in R1 when we swap them if the memory
location for the lock had a zero it
becomes one in the same instruction that
gets us a zero if we do get a zero we
exit this Loop and the lock variable has
become one if however the lock was
already occupied then we swap one with
one I R1 stays one so we keep looping so
until we succeed in obtaining a zero we
will Loop here just as before but also
as we are getting our zero we are
automically setting the lock variable to
one so nobody else can also observe a
zero pretty much if we get a z in our R1
that means that everybody else who try
to do this at about the same time we'll
get our one if somebody else did this
before us then we would be getting their
one in our R1 so the fact that we are
reading zero here means that we are the
ones who acquir the lock so Atomic
exchange gives us this read and write at
the same time behavior that we want to
implement our locks and as you can see
the log function can be now very
simple the drawback of the atomic
exchange operation is that it keeps
writing to the memory location all the
time even while the lock is busy while
the lock has been locked by some
somebody else so as long as we are doing
this we will be doing these rights even
though we're just getting a one all the
time so the second main type of atomic
instructions is a whole family of things
that can be classified as test and then
write so the idea is that we test the
location and if it satisfies some
conditions then we're going to write but
we don't write all the time so let's say
we have some sort of a test and store
instruction which behaves like this we
read the memory location that we are
addressing and if that location is zero
then we store R1 into it and in that
case R1 becomes one but if the location
wasn't zero then we don't store anything
to that location we just return a z so
the idea here is that we're testing
whether the lock is free if it is free
then we try to write a one in it if it's
not free then we simply continue There
is no point in trying to write to a lock
that we know is not free so we are
avoiding the rights that happen in the
exchange while the lock is actually not
free so this behaves very similarly to
The Exchange except that it only does
the right if the lock has the unlocked
state